Let's go with Arian Garuna.  Are you
ready?  I told the
artificial intelligence to present me with a name I'd mistakenly thought about
in the dark, and I think it
did a great job.  My
artificial intelligence is about
60%.  Artificial intelligence and idiot.
artificial as
mixed and Nagaruna finally
said to him, "You've finished criticizing me
about emptiness. And why does
emptiness mean that there can't be
the four highest truths and everything
is?"  And he said, "Yes, I think you've covered
everything."  No, no, I've already covered everything.  You are not a
Buddhist.  Then Nagaruna tells him, "If you
believe that emptiness means those
things, then you don't understand the
purpose, the
essence, or the importance of
emptiness. You don't understand the purpose, you don't
understand the essence, and you don't understand
what emptiness is all about."
And then the rest of the chapter is
explaining those things, but I thought that
since you guys have nothing to do
today and you could figure out these
three, or I'd like to hear your
opinion about these
three tomorrow.  When Nagaruna says, "You don't
understand the purpose of emptiness,"
when he says you don't understand the essence
of emptiness. And when you don't understand the
point of what emptiness is about
, how the point of
emptiness differs from essence, what I'd like to see is
what you think. By the way, we don't have
any commentary from Arian Nagaruna.
We have Chandrairti, 400, 500 years
later we have Jetson
Ka, but we don't know
exactly what he meant, and
I'm curious what you all might
think. Perhaps I'll discuss it now in
your home, in your retreat hut.
Retreat huts are for cooking it up
here and there. Cook it up in your
retreat, and let's talk about this tomorrow.
We have class
tomorrow. No, we don't have this class
tomorrow. On
Tuesday. Tomorrow we have two
translation classes. Sometimes the organizer of
where I'm teaching a class might
say to me, "Can you move the two classes?" And I
say, "No, they're part of every
program."
So if you want to upset Grandpa,
why not...  You move? Why don't you
move the class? And I say, move your
program.
It's part of every program, I
think. Very
well. Yes,
actually, I get the deepest questions
in the men's restroom. I
'm trying to do my
job, and I can't go anywhere,
and they ask me questions. I'm asking myself
questions. I just got this
question right now in the
men's restroom. If you're the person who
asked me the
question, here's my
answer, and I told you I was going to give it to you.
Basically, this verse
says, "When the Buddhas teach the
Dharma, they use both realities." What
are the two realities? The
illusory reality of the world and the reality that is
insurmountable. Two realities, and it
means that the Buddha needs both
realities. You can't
say the Buddha just spends all his time in
emptiness. That's not the case. They also
need the apparent or normal reality.
They use the normal reality, and they use the
insurmountable reality, and they have to
balance them.
And we have to
balance them. The person in the
restroom was talking about the
normal reality in terms
of having a
job.  It's frustrating that I can't
use emptiness. I
also have to make
money. And I think Ari,
Arian
Agaruna's response addresses that comment in
this verse. This is verse number 8,
verse 8 of chapter 24. And he says,
"Look, you need
both." And I think we've all seen the
extreme of someone who only uses
normal reality. They
just make
money, they just work hard, they
just have kids, they have a
family, and that's all they
do. And then it fails because
impermanence fails. The kids grow up or
the kids
die, the job fails, the business
fails.
Oh, what's worse is that if you're
successful and then you
die, there's no future for those things.
They must
fail, they must cause problems, they have to—
that's their
nature, that's normal reality. And
on the other hand, you have to do retreats at
Diamond Mountain, study emptiness,
study the
classics, sit in one of your five
houses.
You have this other side of things. And
Nagaruna
says, he says you can't have the
second without the
First, you have to have a
life, and then you can make that life
incredible. But don't think you can
make that life incredible without life.
And it's very beautiful, and I've had some
students
insist, my teacher, have a
student. I not only had, I've had
50 years of suffering with my
students, but I suffered with their
students for 25 years.
There was this guy who heard about
renunciation and heard
Laming and said, he came to my teacher and
said, "I'm going to live like a
milarepa." And my teacher said, "Oh,
really?" and said, "Yes, no more of this, no more
of this
work, I'm going to live free like a
milarepa." My teacher said,
"We lived in New Jersey, in a
small
town, and there was a small
forest next to the town, and he said, "I'm
going to go live in the forest."  And my
teacher said, "It's autumn in New
Jersey."  And winter is coming to
New Jersey.  And before
global warming we used to have this thing
called snow, and I'm talking about four
or five feet of snow.
And he said, "I'm going to go and stay in the
fire."  And my teacher said,
"Okay, I'm going to abandon this
impermanence, this family life, and
this job. I'm going to go to the forest."  And
my teacher said, "Okay, that's fine, I'll
see you later."
And when he returned two weeks later
, he would sit at the
kitchen table and eat everything in the
refrigerator.  He said, "That forest, in that
forest there are no
refrigerators."  Yes, you know?
And
refrigerators come from
something called money, and money
comes from working, and he said,
"Oh, you need both."  The hen here
is saying that you need both.
You need normal reality, you need
unsurpassable reality.  And in fact they
support each other, they go hand in hand, have a good
job, receive a good salary, don't
go crazy, don't work 18 hours a
day.  Every job in the universe
creates something that people want, that's why they
pay you.  And that helps people.  If
you build houses, if you make
refrigerators,
if
you construct, if you create cars, my dad, I
thought he was this
terrible imperialist capitalist,
because he
built, he built neighborhoods.  I
was always afraid to introduce him to
my teacher, and finally they had to
meet, and I felt embarrassed.
My wife met my dad.  She
arrived when she was 16 and spent time with
us.  I didn't want my dad, the
capitalist, to meet my teacher, the
dharma man.  And then they sat
together in the kitchen of the
Mongolian temple.
And my teacher saw my dad and said, "I've
heard you're a great
businessman. I
've heard you build houses for
people, big neighborhoods,
hundreds of houses," he said.
"Yes," he said, "that is a great dharma."  And
I said,
"What's that?"  He said, "It's a
dharma activity. You're giving so many families
a place to stay. You're a great
bodyad. I'd like to be like you." And I
was like, what? What's
going on? And after that, my dad
said, "I used to wish you were
a Catholic father, but now I think
this is a good thing for
you." In this
verse, Alan Garuna says, "You need
both."
And the
final argument he makes here is very
sexy.  When Buddha taught you
emptiness in the
deer park, at the peak of the vultures,
when he taught the heart sutra at
the peak of the vultures, he used
words, he wrote
something, people wrote the
heart sutra.
Yes, that is not the insurmountable reality,
that is the deceptive reality, that is the
normal reality.  The books, the
teachings, the
translations, the programs at Diamond
Mountain are
normal reality.  We're going there and we're going to eat
normal food.  Wait.  Someone had to
pay for it.  And by the way, the sponsor
who
paid for the student center
is Dr. Wo.  He is very, very kind.  The
first day I met him he said to me, "Is there
anything you need?"  If I need a
coffee shop.  And he said to me, "How much is it going to
cost? You always give double the amount
to a sponsor."
I thought 100,000, but I said 200,000 and he
said, "I'll cover it."
I said, "Wow."  And we built it and it came out
to 1.2 million and I had to go with him
and he
paid for it.  If you ever see him or take a
class with him this week, you should
thank him and be very, very grateful
to
him.  Do you want to hear a secret?
There was this
translator, there was a translator to
talk to him, and there was this woman who
was living in W and she said, "I
translate."  And I started by saying, "
Oh, we don't have a cafeteria."  And she
started
crying, and then the sponsor said, "Do
you need more money?"   I
always carried it with me after
that.
Shin.  So you need both, you need
a
construction company.  It's a good thing those
people aren't dharma students.
They can count, they can build, they can
put on the
roof.  A truly good
dharma student must be both.  That's what
Ariana Garuna is saying in this
verse.  You need
both.  There has to be an
organization, there have to be buildings, there have to
be books, there has to be
money to make the weapon.  They go hand in
hand.  And that's what he's saying in
this verse.  And it doesn't mean that the
business doesn't have to be
dirty, unpleasant.  The business can
be tantric, and we've already talked about
this.  Business can be the path to
diamonds.  If you do business with the
right mindset, it's an
incredible practice.  You have to have that state of
mind.  And in fact, the two need
each other.  What Nagayuna says to the one who
is criticizing him is,
look,
you need what we call the
deceptive reality, which means
normal reality.  You need normal reality
in order to study
unsurpassable reality.  You need both.  You need to
have both.  Who invented that?  Buddha,
not
me.  It
says here, when the Buddha teaches the dharma, he
needs both.  They both need it.  Someone
has to pay for the air conditioning.
Okay.  You need
both.  It's very
beautiful.
Okay.  That?
Wait a
second,
excuse me.  Let's try this one.  What is the
next
image?
Yes, Nagarjuna says you need a
balance between deceptive reality and
insurmountable reality.  I like this one.
What's it called?
Subaja.  I don't know why it's so difficult to
find pictures of this
seesaw.  And he says, "Without relying on
terms, on words. If you don't
depend on words, you can never
reach the unsurpassable reality.
Words are the deceptive,
unsurpassable reality. They are not the
unsurpassable reality, but they are the highest cause and
effect. Without words,
you could not reach the
unsurpassable reality. And without unsurpassable reality, you cannot
reach Nirvana. Without
emptiness, you cannot reach Nirvana.
And the Tibetan language
is, you cannot teach the Dharma without
words, without terms, but
words are not unsurpassable reality,
they are deceptive reality. So you need
deceptive reality. You need false reality
to reach true reality.
Okay, but what Nagayuna is saying
has a very famous line. When
someone says, "Tell me, really, what is it that you
truly believe, what is your true
position?"
I believe what the
farmers believe.  That's his
famous phrase.  Canadians, take care of the
trees.  What they believe, I
believe.  He said, "I believe what
farmers, sowers, believe.
No sower believes you can have
a tree without a
tree. A tree without a seed, sorry.
Next
image. A weird image. I
tried. You don't know how hard I tried with
this image. Like half an hour negotiating
with the AI. I wanted
a woman taking a
jewel off the head of
a
snake. The AI ​​doesn't
know what's possible or impossible. They just
do what you tell them. I tried like 20
times.
And this was the best. I don't know what that
red thing is that she has in her eye. Sorry
. I'm going to spend an extra hour getting it off
.
No, here's the
verse. When
people disrespect
emptiness or say, 'Emptiness is
stupid' or 'I don't understand emptiness,'
what's the point of emptiness?
How is emptiness going to help you think
that something is empty? I don't
understand. When they speak ill of
emptiness, those of little wisdom
are
ruined."  They're ruined.
And then he has an
example. And in
ancient times, if
you want to go back to ancient times, it was believed
that very venomous snakes
had a jewel here, a red jewel,
like a ruby ​​or
something. He said that people who
disrespect the idea of ​​emptiness
or who try to study emptiness and
don't understand it are like people who
seek out venomous cobras to take
the jewel from their
heads and end up dying
because the cobra
bites them. And everything Ariana Nagayuna
says is deeper.
There's always a deeper meaning for
Ariana Nagayuna. And what he's saying
is that the study of emptiness is
dangerous; it's like a
cobra, and you can take the emptiness from
it, you can take the
emptiness, you can take the
jewel, because this snake is
important to him, because he is
Nagayuna.
His name means he is the king of
snakes, the king of
cobras. And by the
way,
Shensong, who walked for
17 years through  So many countries in Asia to
bring Buddhism to China in the Tang
Dynasty for Kang Tyson, who wanted to
kill him and then wanted to give him a tower.
He
visited a great library in southern
India. I think it was John Brady's previous life
, or something like that. And
Shenson visited Ariana Nagaruna's library
. Ariana Nagaruna was a
book collector. He tried to
save the books of his time. She was the one
of his times. He had a
great
library and he thought it was very
important to save the books and he spent a
lot of his
life saving
books, the ultras, the early
ultras, and he was trying to save them. He
built a library and was
trying to save them.
Books went there, he came home with 1000
books, two
translators translated them,
sorry, and he heard that there were some
books missing in this
world. And anyone who has seen
Lord of the Rings knows that
Smog, the
dragon, they like
shiny and precious things, especially
gold and
diamonds. So when  Dragons
hear that there is something valuable, they
try to collect it, to accumulate it,
then they sit on
it and make sure no one uses it,
which is what people do with
money.
So, Nagarin heard that the
dragons had certain
scriptures that they had taken back to their
home, to their
world. So he learned to speak their
language, to speak with them, and he
became their master.
Master means Arjuna, the great
archer of the Bhagavad Gita, the great
shooter of arrows. So he
became the great master of the
dragons, and he gathered the Boroboromido,
the Prashna Paramita of these dragons,
of these nagas, and brought them back
to this world. So he knows about
approaching a dangerous serpent being
and extracting its most
important jewel. So when he mentions it
here, you have to know the story
behind it. And he says that emptiness is
like this jewel on the dragon's forehead, and
approaching a poisonous serpent is
dangerous, and it might
bite you.  You have to think about
that. Why does Nagaruna
say it doesn't require much thought?
People who don't know what they're
doing try to learn emptiness
from someone who doesn't understand it, and then they
say, "Close your
eyes."
In Chinese, it's said to mean black.
Black.
In rock and roll, it is.
Hey, just close your eyes and think of
nothing, and then you've already been bitten by the
snake. If you try to learn
emptiness from someone who doesn't know what
emptiness is, you're going to get stung by the same
emptiness, you're going to get bitten by the same
emptiness. What do you think it is when you get
bitten by fake emptiness? You spend your whole
life walled up in a monastery and trying
to think of nothing. You spend your whole life
trying to empty your
mind, and then you get the poison. You would have been
better off
working at the gas station your whole life
than sitting and staring at a wall and trying to
think of nothing, because that is the
ultimate waste of your human life. You don't
even get paid for that. At least
at the gas station, you  They pay,
right?
Okay. He says
that it hurts you, and then he gives
another example, which is called
Wia, like
Tarane in the mantras of the Buddha. And he
says, "People who use a darani and
don't know what they're doing can be
bitten by the
darane." And I think it was
Juan Hasso who mentioned
yesterday that if you're really interested
in the practice of Buddha medicine,
please read the essay in the book you just
received
that explains how
mantras work, or else the
mantra will bite you, and then you'll
die, and the people you're trying to
help with the mantra will get
sicker and sicker. It won't work.
I think worse than disaster is when it does
n't work.
Dying of cancer is one thing, doing
mantras and then dying of cancer, that's
frustrating.
Okay. Anyway, Ariana Gary
says you need emptiness to
understand mantras. You need
emptiness, and receiving emptiness has to be done
wisely and
carefully. You don't ask a...
A rattlesnake, an
Arizona rattlesnake, will give you
the jewel on its forehead without you making a
good bargain.
It's
interesting. People who study
emptiness the wrong way get
hurt. It's interesting. You can
imagine, right?
Sorry, I have 100 pages of
notes and it's a little
misleading. What's the next image?
What number is it? I'm
going to tell you what number it is.
[Music]
Hold on.
6.11. What's 6.10?
Okay, here we go.
Yes,
this
image—because I write the
DCI courses, I
like to find modern images that
represent
old images. This one
represents Lord Buddha's doubt about
teaching for 7 weeks. After he was
eliminated, he didn't want to teach for 7 weeks.
This is what this image represents.
When you see this image, it's like the
teacher sat in the classroom and
wasn't comfortable teaching yet.
Ariana
Garuna in this chapter
says, Lord
Buddha was
aware that if he didn't teach the
Emptiness, very carefully, people
were going to understand it, they weren't going to understand it
well. And I say that in the last 1000
years more people have understood it
incorrectly than people who have
understood it
well. I hear it all the
time, I
hear things from strange people
that emptiness means try to
think of nothing
empty, you don't have to be nice to
people, everything is empty
anyway, and things
like that. Why do you think this image
relates to that?
Well, it does
mean that Nagarun is admitting
that emptiness is
difficult. And he says, "And why on earth do
you think Buddha sat there saying
nothing for seven
weeks?"  He was
afraid not only that no one would
understand, but that they might
misunderstand him." And he thought it
was better not to talk about
it. So here's the one
who best explains the emptiness in the
world of the second Buddha. And he says, "And
why do you think the Buddha hesitated to teach
if it wasn't
dangerous?"  If it weren't so easy to
misunderstand it, why do
you think the Buddha didn't want to
teach it and structure it in an
interesting way?
The sacred heart of the
Buddha.  Uh,
he had the sacred heart of the Buddha.   He
hesitated to speak because he was afraid
that people would
misunderstand him, and above all he said, "Ah,
things are
empty, I can do whatever I want, everything
is empty, I can do whatever I want."
He was afraid that people
would think that, and that's why he refused to
teach.  He's talking to someone like that
.  What are you saying to the other
person?  You are the person for whom
Buddha did not speak.  Okay,
you understand that people like you are the
reason why Buddha didn't speak.
Perhaps he is finally
criticizing them.  Now if I had to pick
one verse from the 40 verses of this
chapter which is called an examination of
the four highest truths, if
you listen if I should pick the
most famous verse, I would pick this one that
follows.  And because my Sanskrit teacher
was, he got very involved in
statistics.  He would make
handwritten notes of how many
words were mentioned in a book, he would
count them and it was like a
statistical approach to the study
of the classics and that's how I was
taught in a way.  So
when I write an introduction in the
Mixed Nots books, I like to be
able to
clearly state what Nagaruna's most famous verse is
.  Which one have I
used the most in the last 2000 years?  The one I
've used the most, what are the top 10,
what is the biggest hit of all time
if this is one of them.
I do weird things like that.  Where was I?   I
was doing it in
Peru.  In Lima, in a
cafe with Stanley and Alison.  I
forgot, for
Nagaruna.  This is one of the most
famous verses.  This is in the top
10. Everything is correct with anything
for which emptiness is correct.
If emptiness doesn't fit with something,
then nothing will fit with that thing.
If something fits with emptiness, then everything
fits with it.  They're like jeans,
and I'm not going to
use the example I always use.  It's like a pair of jeans
.  They will remain if there is
emptiness.  And you won't have any left if there's no
emptiness.
And this one is very famous, very
famous.  If it's empty, everything is fine.
If it's not empty, it's a
disaster.  Nothing works without
emptiness.  Don't think that emptiness
means nothing is working.  Emptiness
means that everything works.  If it's not
empty, it can't work.  Let's talk
about pens,
a simple
and 100% correct demonstration.  And if you don't
believe it, then I accidentally built a
billion-dollar business,
which is possible, but unlikely.
What is the emptiness of this pen?
The origination depends on this.
What does it mean that all things
depend on something else?  What does it
really mean?  And it just means that it comes from
seeds in your mind.  I've heard these
sociological books about Buddhism, which
means that we are all connected,
blah, blah, blah.   That is
not what dependent origination means
.  It simply
means that everything comes from seeds in
your mind.  That's all simple.  And that
comes from how you treat others.
Therefore, it all comes down to how you treat
others.  That's all.
Zero.  That is
dependent laination.  Don't worry about
anything else.  The pen is coming.
This pen came from a factory in
Japan or from the mind of G Michael.  wine
from the seeds in your
mind.  The factory also came from the
seeds in my
mind, and that is
dependent origination.  So, what is the
emptiness of the
pen?  For
000 and you can't raise your hand before I
ask the question.  For
$0,000 if you find the money,
honey, for $
0,000, what's a good way to
teach
emptiness to a large audience of
people?  Ask them to aim at something.
Yes.
Left hand.  Left hand.  The
Diamond Way, hidden Buddhism for the rest of
your life.  If you want to teach
emptiness, say, raise your left hand,
point your finger at this finger.  Don't use
another finger, especially in Arizona.   They
all have guns.
Write something down in this
room that doesn't come from the seeds
in your mind, and then you have to make it
dramatic.  You can't do it alone.   Ha ha ha.
And you must
do it, and then don't forget what
you have to do.
And then you have to do like this, you can't
just do it, you have to do it like this
and that's emptiness, that's all.
That is a perfect lesson in
emptiness.  That is a
perfect master of emptiness.  Did you understand?
Yes. So why were you upset with
your husband last week?
There's an old joke about Diamond Mountain
because old men forget
which jokes they've already told and which ones they've
told.  We just finished that topic at
Diamond Mountain.  I don't know, it was like
years ago.  Nobody is here.  Who was in
that group?  And one
person was a new person and came
to visit and only after that class were they
always complaining near
Diamond Mountain.  It was difficult,
we had nothing and they were always
complaining, and when he arrived we said to him, "Are you
okay?"  And he said, "I'm surrounded by
idiots."
And we were in a circle around
the people and then we all did it like that,
understanding that it means we come from
you.  Okay.  And there is no greater emptiness than
this.  That's
all.  If things are empty, everything
works.  If things aren't empty,
nothing
works.  He said the opposite at the
beginning of the chapter and he took the most
important thing, the four, the first
teaching of the Buddha, the four truths
of the area and he said, "Emptiness cancels
these four."  And we say, "No,
if the four truths have emptiness, it
works. And if they don't, they don't work."
Okay?  Do you understand?
This verse is very, very
famous.  Sometimes they should memorize
a verse.  If you want to learn
Sanskrit, there is no
clearer and more meaningful Sanskrit than this
verse.  By the way, I'm using a
comment by Chony Lama
Dragedrup from about 300 years ago.   I'll
translate it someday if I ever
have the time and people stop
asking me for
things.  Yes, we're going to do a question and
answer session in 12 minutes.  Team, are you
okay?
Yes.
Okay.
Following.  Yes, I think it's the
18th, verse 18. If you did the
statistical analysis, this is a very
popular chapter over the last 2000 years.  It's
like
a song that was a
hit.  And by the way, if they ask you what
the middle way is, what does
Madamica mean?  This is the
answer.  Who
better than Nagayuna to say that it is the
middle way?
This is a super famous verse where
Ariana Agaruna explains what the middle way is
and he
says what we
call dependent origination.  What does
dependency mean?  That everything comes from
the seeds in your mind.  When I say
dependency, I hate that word.   It
just means that things come from
seeds in your mind about how you treat
others.  That's
dependent origination.  That's all.  That is
emptiness.  Who
said
Nagaruna?  He should know.  That is
emptiness.  Technically it's
emptiness, isn't it?  Emptiness is a
negative thing.  Dependence is a
positive thing.  Tell me how the
ways work.  Tell me how they work.
They come from your seeds.  Tell me how they don't
work.  They don't come from seeds in your
mind.  Emptiness is always something that
is missing, that is not there
.  Dependent origination is something
that is always there and
therefore cannot be the same.
Technically, logically they cannot be
the same.  One is an absence, the other is
another presence.  They cannot be the
same.  And then
he says, do you want
to know what dependency means?  What is
emptiness?  The fact that things
are labeled.
Labeling is an expression for creating
seeds in your
mind.  This is a
pen.  You label it as a
pen.  That's why we call it a
pen.  That's not why we call it
labeling.  It usually means a
name you give it, like a
price tag you put on it, but that's not what it
means in the
middle way; it means it comes from your
seeds, labeled by your mind.  And
that process of making labels is always
done with mental images.  The
seed opens in your mind and a mental image
emerges and covers
it.  I love using the image of
snow.
Two scoops of vanilla ice cream at the
Moscato restaurant and then you
say, "Put
chocolate sauce mixed with
heavy coffee on it and the image is covering the
stick and then it becomes a pen."
So when they say just the name
they mean the image, or when they say
tag it means I've been
tagged with images and that's why
a dog can see it and say, "I'd
like to bite it."  By the
way, the dog thing sounds easy, it
sounds very
simple, it sounds like Gel is
trying to be easy.  I'm not
trying to do it.  If a
dog sees something different, if a dog
wants to bite this instead of writing a
poem with it, it proves the emptiness of
the
pen and you don't need 2000 years of the
house of classics.  In
truth, if a dog sees something
different, it checks for emptiness.  That's
all.  So simple.
So simple.  And nobody in the universe
can argue with you that you're wrong.  No, it's just that a
dog sees it as a feather and
forgot about it.  You can't say that.  If a dog
really sees something
different, which is proven by how they
react, they bite it, they don't write,
they must be seeing something different and
that proves that the thing is empty.  You don't
need anything else.  That's
all.  The fact that a dog cannot see a
pen is proof of
Buddhism.  It is proof that
Buddhism is correct and it is
proof that
you can not die if you understand
Buddhism well.  The dog is proof, it
's
evidence, and nobody has managed to prove to me
that it isn't evidence.  Someone
in Florida tried it.  It had to be from
Florida.  I'm not just
saying
something funny happened there recently
and the fact that the
pen comes from your
seeds, what's the bottom line
here?  That's the
middle way.  Don't ask me what's going on.
Matamaca.  By the way, both are
correct.  Don't ask me what the
middle way is.  That's the middle way.
Things are somewhere in between, between
dependence and privacy.  And that is the
middle way, and that is the highest school
of Buddhism.  There is nothing higher than that
.  And that is also the Buddhism
used for tantra.  The path of the diamond
depends on
Madamica.  Diamond Way is a
school in Madagascar.
Okay
, we have 4 more minutes.
Okay,
okay.  These great Buddhist thinkers
are also very tender.  They do
cute things.  I think he would play Jimmy
Henrik if he were here.  So
someone has to tell me the next
verse, because this is
sweet.  I'm not going to offer money.  Can you
scream?  Yes.
He's using the opponent's logic
against his opponent, which is what he
always ends up
doing, similar to a husband and
wife.  He's saying,
listen.  He uses, by the way, listens to the
uses of the same Sanskrit words that
the opponent uses in the first line and
returns saying, "You know
what,
sweetheart? If things aren't
empty, then the four truths
are wrong."  Because the other one
started the chapter by saying, "These
things are empty."  Therefore, all
four truths are wrong.  He
says, we're at verse 20, we're
halfway through the chapter.  Did you know
?  When I reflect on this,
I think that if things are not empty,
the four truths are wrong.
He's using the same words, he's
using the same language against the
guy.  At this point he has already explained about
the mind seeds and he has already explained
about the pen and he says, "You know what?
When I think about it, if
things are as you
say, then there are no four
truths."  And by the way, I didn't add
the following series of arguments to the class.
If there is no emptiness, there are no four
truths of the area and you cannot
relate to them and you cannot obtain
the results of those four
and go through
everything.  If things aren't empty,
we have a problem.
Okay, very good.  That's very sweet and
typical of Nagardina.  Let me see how I'm doing
with my time.  I think I have some
left, we have to finish
this.  I know the questions and
answers are coming up, let's finish right after.   I'm
going to try to
stay here and continue with this because
we have to finish the whole book.
Okay.  Next
image.
[Music]
Gibson, can you read Tibetan?
Kak, by the way,
yes.
We have written the
classics using Roman letters.  Why do
n't we use Chinese characters or
Hebrew characters?  When we started the project in
1983, in '83 at Pine Hall, all the
computers in the world were based
on those characters and used
Roman characters.  So we started entering the
data in
Roman characters.  It's a weakness of the
Shensen Tower classics.
Translators are not used to
reading
wood carvings,
wood engravings.  There's a problem with the wood; there are
knots in the wood, and sometimes
they cause
the letters to twist so they fit into
the wood.  That's why we have people
there.  We don't have the
optical
character recognizer.  It has many
errors, so here you can see the
problem.  Now, according to
Gibson, who is
Busuku?  Master Shantideva.  Very good.
This is the nickname of Master
Shanti Deva and it
means lazy, good, good for nothing,
idle.  So if you want to give a
big one, if you want to say something nice to
your friend, you're Chantiva, you're just a
busuku.
Why did the people in his monastery
think he was a lazy good-for-
nothing?  But in fact he was busy
writing at home and
couldn't do all the other activities
that people
expected.  And then he wrote one of the
greatest books ever
written.  And
I, I, uh, uh, I hesitated a
lot to remove it from the
requirements.  It's the 10th, 11th, and 12th.
Uh, I hesitated a lot before removing it from the
requirements because otherwise it
gets too long.  Busuko is the master
of Bodhisattva activities.  Nobody
wrote a better book on the
lifestyle of a Bodhisattva than
Busuku than Shantireva.  Incidentally, in
ancient carvings it is called
Busuku.  He seems proud.  Are you
calling me Mr. Lazy?  I am, I
am, darling.  Know?  I'm so lazy you
have no idea.  And all his work was
secret.  So Arian Agaruna says, "If
things
are as you want them to
be and are not empty, then there is no
Buddha and no bodar.
Body avatara. Then there is no
bodhisattva lifestyle. According to you, he
is really attacking the person. First he
said, "Yes, you are right.  There are no Four
Truths of the realm if things are not
empty." And then he says, "And by the way, there
are no Three Jewels if things are not
empty, because there is no Buddha if things
are not empty." And you can't
become a Buddha because there are no Six
Perfections according to you.
Right now
, Arian Agayun is criticizing
the other person. According to you, the Six
Perfections don't exist. They're outside
the window, and Shantiva was perhaps just
Busuku wasting her time.
Okay. So when you see this picture, you're
going to remind yourself that without emptiness, there are no
Bodhisattvas. Forget the Three Jewels. There are
no Bodhisattvas.
No one could be a Bodhisattva without
emptiness. You can't practice
Buddhism, the Six Perfections, if you don't
understand emptiness. And that emptiness is
what makes them
perfect. This is the last one, and then
we're going to do a question and answer.
Ready?
There are new books by Rosa Vanicken.
You should thank her, you should
say hello. Thank you.
She's doing  Two incredible things.
He's in charge of publishing all the
Mixns Nots translations. There are 15
books that must be...
Nobody has done this for the last 14
years. Nobody has done this for the last
years. Yes.
Nobody has done this. What we're
doing in 600 years is
incredible. And a lot of this is due to
Rosa. When you see her, you should
thank her, but he was working
hard. He did two
incredible things. So some of my
books that I did, I did with a big
publisher in New York, and they have the
copyright. I can't print them. They
have the rights. She negotiated the
rights with them, so we have the
rights to print a certain number of
my own
books.
Thank you. Because they keep making books and they do
n't want to give us the rights. So
we bought the rights. She did something
incredible. And a couple of these books are
anniversary books. It's the
25th anniversary of when I wrote *
The Garden*,
which is about an
amazing angel, and it's like 30 years since
I translated the main teachings of
Buddhism and the
Yoga Sutras. So  which we had permission to
republish. Now you can
get the books. So there's a
QR code. Do you know what to do with the
QR code?
So we've made a
hardcover edition of the meditations on
emptiness by Venerable Utala Bets
Gear. It's the best book on
emptiness meditations you can buy and includes
all the details of a
proper meditation technique. Even if you don't
want to see the part about
emptiness, the second part is how to
meditate and it's camashila. The
instructions on camashila are how to
meditate. Those books are
available. I'm not
advertising,
I'm just highlighting what Nagaruna says at the
end here. And by the way, we just
finished this book, this chapter,
sorry.
He says, "If you truly understand
emptiness, you understand the
seeds."  If you are a master of
emptiness, you understand the seeds."
And it came to pass, and from that
statement arose a very famous genre
of
literature where people sing
love songs to Lord Buddha for
teaching dependence.
You are so beautiful that you taught
seeds, you taught emptiness in the
seeds. So, this whole theme of
chants, and there's a whole collection of
songs that are to Lord Buddha. You are
so beautiful because you taught emptiness
through the seeds, and the
important part is through the seeds.
And the most beautiful song of this is
Tendr Tupa, which means praise to
Lord Buddha for teaching emptiness in the
form of
seeds. There's a translation of that and a
commentary. They're going to finish it tomorrow.
Gibson is going to finish it tomorrow. You can
be there.
It's in the last few lines, and it keeps going and going,
and it keeps getting
slower as we get closer to
finishing. It's like asking your husband
to clean the toilet. It's going to get slower and
slower. I think we have to finish
tomorrow. I think we can't stretch it out any
longer.
And this is where it comes from. This is the
verse from where it comes. The last verses
of this chapter are where Nagaruna says,
"Look, there's nothing sexier than
dependent origination.  Embracing emptiness.
If you really understand them, you see them as
a
couple, so talk about
it.
Okay. Follow the Q&A so
no one can say we didn't do Q&
A.
First, thank you very much for
showing it to her.  I think he was there
when
ACI started.
I have been thinking a lot about
truth and the nature of truth,
particularly the truth of the law of
karma, which is very close to confirming
that if the law of
karma is self-existent, what is
happening in the world today, how are we to think
about
the truth of the law of karma?
And yes, it's like the truth of 2 + 2 equals
4. And how do you relate that to what
the truth seems to be for other
people?  For
example,
certain people
who say that the fastest way to
paradise is to contain extreme violence
towards other people.  and how could we
define what is
true?  Thank you so much.  I'm going to say what I
'm
thinking, and I think what Buddhism would
say
is what we call the three
golden tests, and it took me a long time to
understand it, and I kept going back and
studying them again and again.  In
ancient times, when you bought
a
horse, you paid, you paid with corn or
something like that.  400 pieces of corn, right?   There were
no 390.  What do we call it in China?
Alipay.  There was no Alipay.   There
were no credit cards before
.  Before there were
credit cards there was no cash, so
before that there were gold coins and
before there were gold coins there was no
corn.  So when
you bought a horse and agreed on how many
pieces of corn, and in fact the
ancient way of burning money was to burn
grains, and that's what the
fire offering means.  I have more faith in Buddha than in
the grocery store.  I'm going to burn
money as an offering to the
Buddha and I won't be able to use that money
after that.  I won't be able to eat it
afterwards.  I believe in Buddha so much that I'm
going to burn my money and
offer it to him.  That is what a
fire offering is.  People started using
pieces of gold, and then
dishonest people emerged and
began covering the lead with gold.
And then came something called the
three
golden trials.  Se
che means burn it, chin means
cut it and luego means
file it.  How to establish the truth?  It's
the three gold medals.  This is
traditional.  This is traditional language.   It
goes back, it goes back to the times of
horses.  Sex
means a part of deciding whether something
is true or
not.  It's possible to confirm it with your
direct,
personal experience.  That's difficult.  In the
case of
jihad, have you killed an infidel and
gone to heaven?  I don't know, I haven't gotten
that far.
That would be a
direct experience.  In this case it's not practical,
I suppose.  And then there's a second test,
which is,
hey, you cut the gold and see what's
inside with metal scissors or something
like that, and that refers to confirming something
with logic.
And that's how the Buddhist would respond,
saying that there is a
consistency between cause and effect.
When you plant a pumpkin seed,
when you plant an apple, you get
an apple.  When you sow, you don't have
happiness.  We would say that's
illogical.  Simply put,
forget about religion and forget about
how you were raised.  It doesn't make sense to
plant a hot chili pepper and get
a banana.  They are not similar, so it is
illogical to say that violence
could take you to heaven.  That's the
second test.  Tar.  What is a star?
It's like
filing it down.  And by the way, these are like
damning evidence that I know is not
encouraged in the diamond business.
You don't want to crush a diamond to see
if it's real, but the third option is to file it down
and see if it's lead inside,
and that would be, what do you
call it?  You can say it like an
authority.
Authority is
deceptive, and the type of authority, as the
definition of authorities has been
followed so far, has been followed, and everything has turned out
well.  That's the best thing you can say
with authority.  Authority is a
bit weak compared to logic.
Authority
means Ges Michael up until now in my
life what he has said what he has told me
that I have tried and so far I have
tried and it worked and now he is telling me that I shouldn't
kill people because I'm not going to go to
Nirvana, but because of what he has
told me, everything he has told me in the
past, as everything that has worked in the past
, I am going to accept it and that is
weak because it would be Ges Michael
failing this last one.
These are the three golden tests, but
if you find a person who is
trustworthy—that's why you have to spend
so much time choosing a
spiritual teacher—you have to check them out,
check them out, check them out, and then you start
following what they
said.  That's what a Buddhist
would answer.  Those are the three
real tests.  And if they pass those
tests, then we would say that it's
possible, which is probably
true.  Very good, very good.  Now it's
true that I'm going to have
breakfast, I don't know about you.
Yes, so I say it's true.  Now they're going
to decipher it to see if I'm telling
the truth or not.  Very well,
thank you very much.  Okay.